Finding Aid for Wilson I. Davenny papers, 1889-1917
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Wilson I. Davenny papers 1889-1917
Davenny, Wilson Imbrie, 1859-1917.
3 linear feet and 1 oversize folder
851068 Aa 2; UAm
Newspaperman, lobbyist for the National Rivers and Harbors Congress, and spokesman for the United Spanish War Veterans. Correspondence, scrapbooks, speeches, business papers and account books relating primarily to his work as a lobbyist.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection came from Mr. and Mrs. Donald Adams (donor no. 857 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Wilson I. Davenny was a veteran of the Spanish-American War. In his career, he was newspaperman for the New York Tribune, field secretary for the National Rivers and Harbors Congress, a waterways lobby, and assistant adjutant general of the United Spanish War Veterans organization.
The Davenny collection is comprised of the following series: Correspondence and other papers; United Spanish War Veterans Organization; National Rivers and Harbors Congress; and Other materials. The National Rivers and Harbors Congress series provides insight into the financing and operation of the lobby. Much of the correspondence in this series is with M.A. Thompson, secretary and treasurer of the organization.
Subjects:
Lobbying.; National Rivers and Harbors Congress.; United Spanish War Veterans.; Veterans--Michigan--Societies, etc.; Spanish-American War, 1898
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Cuba.; Davenny, Wilson Imbrie, 1859-1917.; Maine (Battleship); Military art and science.; Spanish-American War, 1898
Contributors:
Ransdell, Joseph Eugene, 1858-1954.; Smith, Samuel William, 1852-1931.; Washington, Booker T., 1856-1915.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Tintypes.
- Correspondence and other papers
  - 1889-1933, 24 folders (Box 1)
    (include letter from Booker T. Washington, 1911, and from Rep. Samuel Smith, May 11, June 15 and June 22, 1914)
- United Spanish War Veterans Organization
  (and related organizations)
  - 1898-1916, 11 folders (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1901-1912, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Speeches (Box 2)
  - Spanish War Review, 1911-1912 (Box 2)
    (Davenny was editor and manager during this period)
- National Rivers and Harbors Congress
  (waterways lobby; Davenny was field secretary)
  - 1912-1917 and undated, 25 folders (Box 2)
- Other materials
  - Letters containing endorsements of Davenny for US Consular Service, 1897 (Box 2)
  - Abstracts, deeds, and inventory of the Davenny library (Box 2)
  - Cash book, 1909 (Box 2)
  - Scrapbooks, 1903-1906, 8 volumes (Box 3)
    (probably clippings of articles that Davenny wrote for the New York Tribune )
  - Pocket expense books, 1906-1909 (Box 3)
  - Photograph album relating to the raising and commemoration of the U.S.S. Maine in 1912 (Box 3)
  - Photograph: portraits of Davenny, his wife, and acquaintances, 2 folders (Box 3)
    (see also oversize folder UAm)